Jane Harman Papers, 1960-1998 (ongoing) (bulk 1993-1998)
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
- SERIES IV. LEGISLATIVE FILES 1993-98, 61 linear ft.
  In addition to writing and sponsoring bills, Harman also contributed to official legislative letters that were sent to colleagues, the White House, or other government agencies. Co-signed letters represents the letters Harman co-signed from the 105th Congress (1997-98). They are arranged alphabetically by the topic assigned by Harman's office staff. The topics range greatly from AIDS drug assistance program funding to Land and Water Conservation Fund funding to transit projects in California.
  As part of her legislative responsibilities, Harman served on a number of committees during her tenure. The House National Security Committee subseries contains copies of files from this committee for the 104th and 105th Congresses. These files are closed for 30 years until January 1, 2029 according to Rule XI and Rule XXXVI of the Rules of the House of Representatives of the 105th Congress. The committee files are arranged chronologically by Congress and then alphabetically by topic within a Congress. Although there are no other file groups specifically identified as committee files for the other committees on which Harman served, committee-related materials can be found in the Legislative staff files, especially in Ron Stone's files, and in Subject/issue files, mainly in Defense and Women in the armed forces. See the Appendix for a listing of Harman's committee assignments for the 103rd-105th Congresses.
  Legislative staff files, dating from 1993 to 1998 with the bulk from 1997 to 1998, represent the work of four Legislative Assistants and the Legislative Director of Harman's legislative staff: Maria Alongi (1997-98?), Bryan Banks (1998), David Flanders (1995-98), Danny Geffen (1993-96?), and Ron Stone (1993-96?). David Flanders was the Legislative Director from 1995 to 1998 and then Chief of Staff from June 1998 to December 1998. The work of additional members of the legislative staff (John Conger, George Raach, Mary Vesely, and Mike Hammon) can be found throughout SERIES IV. LEGISLATIVE FILES in various subject files. The first folder in this subseries, Legislative assignments, delineates the assignment of legislative topics to various staff members for 1996-98. The staff files are arranged alphabetically by the staff member's last name. Maria Alongi also worked on topics with, or took over responsibilities from, Danny Geffen and Ron Stone and those files are listed under Geffen/Alongi or Stone/Alongi.
  Project files consist of legislative and non-legislative projects in which Harman and her staff were interested or with which they were involved. They date from 1995 to 1998 and are arranged alphabetically by topic.
  Subject/issues files are divided into three areas: Defense, Women in the armed forces, and General. Public hearings and published reports remain open. The files are arranged alphabetically by topic and range from 1993 to 1998. Topics represented in the Defense files are the B-2 bomber, Big Think Forums, defense conversion/dual-use technology, export policy, defense firms, Los Angeles Air Force Base and base realignment/closure, missile defense, military programs, and weapons of mass destruction.
  The Women in the armed forces files are arranged alphabetically by topic and date from 1993 to 1998. Many files in this group relate to integrated training and sexual harassment in the armed forces.
  The General subject/issues files are arranged by Congress and then alphabetically by subject. General - 105th is the largest of the groups and is preceded by Major legislative initiatives and issues - 105th. Files pertaining to specific bills are usually listed by number (e.g., HR 988 - Attorney Accountability Act). Legislative summary files and files descriptive of a session's activities are usually listed first.
  Whip schedules and reports are correspondence and newsletters from the Democratic Whip. They date from the 104th Congress (1995-96) and 1st session of the 105th Congress (1997). The Whips are responsible for rallying their respective parties and coordinating party activities regarding legislation. The Democratic Whip for the 104th and 105th Congresses was David E. Bonior (D-Michigan).
  Briefing books are prepared by Harman's staff or other organizations to provide a concise source of information about a particular topic. They are organized by year, then alphabetically by topic. Briefing books relating to Harman's political campaigns can be found in SERIES III. POLITICAL ACTIVITIES.
  Legislative Weekly Updates are memos to Harman from her legislative staff in Washington, D.C. These serve to update her on current projects and legislation, propose future actions, and provide recommendations on whether to attend various events, sessions, or hearings. These Updates are from 1998; it is not known whether the Updates were produced in earlier years. For updates from her district staff in California, see SERIES VII. OFFICE ADMINISTRATION.
  Research materials are mostly government publications or publications from private organizations that are not widely available elsewhere. These are arranged by year, then alphabetically by author/title.
  Select portions of Alongi's files and Stone's files are closed until January 1, 2029, as noted in the folder list.
  The Defense files are closed until January 1, 2029, because they contain materials relating to the House National Security Committee.
  The Women in the armed forces files are similarly closed until January 1, 2029.
- SERIES V. CONSTITUENT SERVICES 1993-98, 15.5 linear ft.
  This series shows the interaction between Harman and her constituents. It is arranged in six subseries: Constituent mail, District concerns, District visits, Constituent requests, Response form letters, and Response correspondence.
  Constituent mail is incoming correspondence from constituents to Harman's offices from 1993 to 1998. It is arranged chronologically by Congress and session beginning with the 103rd Congress, 1st session (1993) and ending with the 105th Congress, 2nd session (1998). Within a Congressional session, the folders are arranged alphabetically by topic. The topic heading "Random" is the staff's equivalent of miscellaneous letters.
  This subseries was sampled to reduce bulk and represents 20-25% of the original material. The remainder is a representative sample of the original content, given that the sampling method reduced every topic by the same percentage and the original topics remain.
  The District concerns subseries contains materials relating to important issues in Harman's Congressional district. The topics are arranged alphabetically, beginning with Airport issues and ending with Women. Two additional topics, North end of district issues and South end of district issues, follow Women and contain materials specific to certain cities and towns in Harman's district. These are arranged alphabetically by town. Places included in the North end are Lawndale, Marina del Rey, Venice, and Westchester. Places included in the south end are Avalon, El Segundo, Gardena Valley, Hermosa Beach, Lomita, Manhattan Beach, Palos Verdes, Redondo Beach, and Torrance.
  The District visits subseries contains materials on Harman's visits to her district from 1994 to 1998. The visits are organized chronologically. Visits with a special purpose or for a specific event as delineated by her staff are noted.
  In addition to voicing their views on current or upcoming legislation in constituent mail, constituents also asked Harman's office for assistance on more specific matters relating to their communities. Constituent requests contains those requests from 1994 to 1997. Some letters were forwarded to other agencies that could be of more help.
  Due to the volume of correspondence received by a Congressional office, it is difficult for Congresspersons and their staffs to write individual responses. Response form letters contains the form letters that Harman and her staff used to respond to much of the regular constituent correspondence they received. There are various form letters from 1993 to 1998.
  Response correspondence consists of responses to items that Harman's office sent out from 1993 to 1996. Occasionally Harman's office wrote personalized replies to incoming constituent mail using pre-written prints. The original constituent letter often accompanies these.
- SERIES VI. MEDIA ACTIVITIES 1994-98, 2.25 linear ft.
  This series is divided into three subseries: Publications and mailings, General, and Newspaper clippings. In the Publications and mailings subseries, "Legislative Happenings" is a newsletter that Harman sent to her constituents.
  Harman's office staff collected newspaper clippings about Harman and issues that interested her. Only those articles directly pertaining to Harman have been kept in the Newspaper clippings subseries. The clippings are organized chronologically by month.
- SERIES VII. OFFICE ADMINISTRATION 1993-98, 6 linear ft.
  This series represents the overall operations of Harman's offices. The legislative office staff is just one component of the overall staff it takes to successfully operate Harman's district and Washington offices. There are four subseries: Chief of Staff files, Office files, District Office Updates, and Reference materials.
  The Chief of Staff is in charge of the entire staff that works for the Congressperson. From 1993 to 1998, at least four different people held this position in Harman's office and the Chief of Staff files contain materials the chiefs of staff retained and kept separate from other office files. Bill Black has one file that dates from 1993. It is not apparent from the collection whether he was Chief of Staff for the entire 103rd Congress. Mark Kadesh was Chief of Staff from 1995 to 1997. The notebooks contain Kadesh's notes from his day-to-day work and are not dated in any definitive manner. Mike Monasmith was the Chief of Staff from 1997 to 1998. His files are organized alphabetically by topic. David Flanders was the Chief of Staff for the last part of 1998. It does not appear that he kept any specific office files, although his notebooks in SERIES IV. LEGISLATIVE FILES may contain office related content.
  Office files are the general files that the staff used in their daily operations. The "Bible" is the office handbook from the 103rd Congress, although it is not complete. The guestbook lists those visitors who signed in when visiting Harman's district office. The scheduling memos provide insight into how Harman and her staff organized her schedule and decided which events and meetings were worth attending. They are organized chronologically from 1994 through 1998. The General files are arranged by Congress and then alphabetically by topic. Most of those files are from the 105th Congress (1997-98).
  District Office Updates are memos sent to the Washington office to update Harman and the Washington staff on the activities of her district office. They include staff news and assignments, progress reports on constituent issues and notices of important events and activities. They are arranged chronologically.
  Reference materials are the publications and reports that Harman and her staff used to inform themselves on how to operate a Congressional office and the rules of being a Congressperson. They are organized by Congress.
- SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS 1960-98, 1 linear ft.
  This series is arranged in seven subseries, mimicking the topical arrangement of the rest of the collection. The Biographical subseries contains photographs from Harman's youth and of her family. The Professional activities subseries contains images from her time in the White House and as a Senate staff member, including a picture of Harman with Justice Harry Blackmun.
  The Political activities photographs date from 1987 to 1998 and are organized alphabetically by topic. The Legislative activities subseries contains photographs related to Congressional activities and initiatives. They are organized alphabetically by topic and date from 1993 to 1998. The Fort Jackson photographs under Military document Harman's experience with the Army basic training physical fitness testing with the 2nd Battalion, 28th Infantry Regiment.
  The Constituent services subseries, dating from 1995 to 1998, contains various pictures of Harman with constituents and at various constituent events. The Media activities subseries contains publicity and press photos from 1997-98. The Office staff photographs are from 1995 and 1996 and depict various members of Harman's staff as well as her office environment, including her Army Barbie and G.I. Barbie.
- SERIES IX. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS 1992-98, 9.5 linear ft.
  This series contains Audiotapes, Videotapes, Films and Computer media. Arranged chronologically, the Audiotapes feature interviews with Harman on various subjects including NAFTA, defense spending, and gender integration in the military. Only those audiotapes for which there are use copies may be accessed immediately. An asterisk (*) next to a title indicates there is a use copy available. If a use copy does not exist, 3 weeks advance notice must be given for a use copy to be made.
  The Videotapes are arranged chronologically with the bulk of the videotapes dating from 1996 to 1997. Dealing with topics such as women in the military, defense spending, the environment, education and gun control, many of the videotapes feature interviews with Jane Harman on local and national television. In addition, some of the videotapes are promotional material publicizing Harman's candidacies for both the House of Representatives and Governor of California. Only those tapes for which there are use copies may be viewed immediately. An asterisk (*) next to a title indicates there is a use copy available. If a use copy does not exist, 3 weeks advance notice must be given for a use copy to be made.
  Notes, letters, or other written materials accompanied a few of the videotapes; this is indicated in brackets at the end of the title. The written material is in a separate folder at the end of SERIES VII. OFFICE ADMINISTRATION. Some of the tapes are in formats other than VHS; this also is indicated in brackets at the end of the title.
  Although the majority of audiovisual materials are in playable formats, some may require players that are obsolete or that may not be available.
  [Note: Only those materials for which there are use copies may be accessed immediately. An asterisk (*) next to a title indicates there is a use copy available. If a use copy does not exist, 3 weeks advanced notice must be given for a use copy to be made.]
Contents List
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS 1960-1998
  - 1960 Democratic Convention (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Young Citizens for Johnson, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Smith College, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Awards/certificates, 1993-98, [see also Oversize Materials] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Tribute to Harman, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Biographies, 1997-98, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1996-97 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "A Day in the Life of Jane Harman", [see also Oversize Materials] (Box 1)
- SERIES II. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES 1972-92
  - White House
    - Memoranda, 1976-78 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Legal Services Corporation - Board vacancies, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Publications
    - Articles about Harman, 1972-78 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Articles by Harman, 1972-78 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Correspondence
    - 1974-84 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1987 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    - Political contributions and thank yous, 1981-92 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Organizations and conferences
    - Women's Legal Defense Fund, 1971, 1982-85 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Women and the Constitution Seminar, 10-12 Feb 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - National Democratic Institute, 1987-88 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Office files, 1987-92
    [Closed until January 1, 2013]
    - 14 Jan-23 Apr 1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 3 Jan-2 May 1989 (Box 3, Folder 2-7)
    - 2 May-17 Aug 1989 (Box 4, Folder 1-6)
    - 18 Aug-28 Dec 1989 (Box 5, Folder 1-9)
    - 2 Jan-26 Feb 1990 (Box 6, Folder 1-7)
    - 27 Feb-17 May 1990 (Box 7, Folder 1-8)
    - 18 May-11 Sep 1990 (Box 8, Folder 1-8)
    - 12 Sep 1990-22 Jan 1991 (Box 9, Folder 1-8)
    - 22 Jan-27 Jun 1991 (Box 10, Folder 1-7)
    - 2 Jul 1991-19 Nov 1992 (Box 11, Folder 1-8)
    - 24 Nov-10 Dec 1992 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Los Angeles 1991-92 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- SERIES III. POLITICAL ACTIVITIES 1973-98
  - General correspondence (Box 12)
    - 1994-97, [see also SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS-Legislative activities-General; SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS -Legislative activities-Military-Miscellaneous; Oversize Materials] (Box 12, Folder 3-10)
    - 1998 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - Thank yous, 1992-96, [see also SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS-Political activities-Miscellaneous; SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS -Legislative activities-Military-Miscellaneous] (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Thank yous, 1997-98, [see also SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS-Political activities-NFIB/Chamber of Commerce] (Box 13, Folder 4-5)
    - Recommendations, 1992-97 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - White House, 1995-98 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Congratulatory letters, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Agencies, 1996-98 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Governor's race, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Speeches, 1973-80 (Box 15, Folder 1-4)
  - Democratic National Party (DNP)
    - Democratic Platform Committee (DPC) (Box 15)
      - Correspondence, 1980, 1983-84 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence, 1984-85 (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - Geraldine Ferraro, 1983-84, [see also SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS-Political activities-Democratic National Party and Oversize Materials] (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - 1984 Democratic Platform Committee materials (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - 1984 Democratic Platform and National Convention (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Publications, 1980-84 (Box 16, Folder 2-7)
    - Democratic Gala
      - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - Press releases and agendas, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Presidential and Democratic Party Victory Fund, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - National Lawyers' Council
      - Executive Committee: minutes, 1988-91 (Box 17, Folder 3-5)
      - Eu, et al. v. San Francisco Democratic Central Committee, et al., No. 87-1269 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Lawyers for Fair Play, 1988 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Press packets (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - "A Democratic Perspective on Legislative Districting" (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - "Analysis of Constitutionality of Attempts to Limit Tenure of State/Federal Officials" (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Democratic Policy Committee, "The Weekender"
      - 1996-97 (Box 18, Folder 6-9)
      - 1998 (Box 19, Folder 1-5)
    - Democratic Caucus, 1997
      - Part 1 (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - Part 2 (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
    - New Democrat Network, 1997-98 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - California Democratic Delegation, 1998 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Democratic Steering Committee, 1998 (Box 20, Folder 5-7)
  - Campaigns
    - Friends of Jane Harman, 1991-92 (Box 21, Folder 1-7)
    - House races (Box 21)
      - 1992 (Box 21)
        - Working file, [see also Oversize Materials] (Box 21, Folder 8)
        - Media activities: clippings, campaign fliers, [see also Oversize Materials] (Box 22, Folder 1-4)
      - 1994
        - Campaign notebook (Box 22)
          - Part 1 (Box 22, Folder 5-6)
          - Part 2 (Box 23, Folder 1-4)
        - Field notebook (Box 23, Folder 5)
        - Harman International (Box 23, Folder 6)
        - Working files: campaign plan, Brooks, Susan, general (Box 23, Folder 7-9)
        - Clippings (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - 1994 campaign contestation
        - 36th Congressional District Election Hearing (Box 24, Folder 2)
        - Correspondence (Box 24, Folder 3-5)
        - Election fraud investigation status, 1996 (Box 24, Folder 6)
        - General (Box 24, Folder 7-8)
        - Legal documents (Box 24, Folder 9-10)
        - Clippings/press releases (Box 25, Folder 1)
      - 1996
        - Issue files (Box 25)
          - Aerospace/defense jobs (Box 25, Folder 2)
          - Asset forfeiture (Box 25, Folder 3)
          - Choice (Box 25, Folder 4)
          - Gas tax op-ed (Box 25, Folder 5)
          - Seniors (Box 25, Folder 6)
          - Welfare reform (Box 25, Folder 7)
        - Briefing books
          - Debate 1 (Box 25, Folder 8)
          - Debate 2 (Box 25, Folder 9)
          - Debate preparation (Box 25, Folder 10)
          - Daily Breeze Editorial Board (Box 25, Folder 11)
        - Working files
          - 1996 California election calendar (Box 25, Folder 12)
          - Bowen/Harman (Box 26, Folder 1)
          - California Combined Campaign finances (Box 26, Folder 2)
          - Campaign issues (Box 26, Folder 3-4)
          - Campaign notes (Box 26, Folder 5)
          - Campaign plan (Box 26, Folder 6)
          - Candidate profiles (Box 26, Folder 7)
          - Election night party (Box 26, Folder 8)
          - Endorsements (Box 26, Folder 9-13)
          - Field data (Box 26)
            - Part 1, [see also SERIES IX. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS-Computer media] (Box 26, Folder 14)
            - Part 2 (Box 27, Folder 1-2)
          - Field plan (Box 27, Folder 3)
          - Issues research (Box 27, Folder 4-5)
          - Karnette campaign (Box 27, Folder 6)
          - National Committee for an Effective Congress (Box 27, Folder 7)
          - Statement of candidacy (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Governor's race, 1998
      - Briefing books (Box 27)
        - Young Democrats, 12 Mar (Box 27, Folder 9)
        - Inland Empire/Palm Springs, 13 Mar (Box 27, Folder 10)
        - Eureka/Redding trip, 14-15 Apr (Box 27, Folder 11)
        - San Francisco, 1 May (Box 27, Folder 12)
        - Chronicle Editorial Board, 1 May (Box 28, Folder 1)
        - Sacramento Bee Editorial Board, 4 May, [see also Oversize Materials] (Box 28, Folder 2)
        - San Jose Mercury News Editorial Board, 5 May (Box 28, Folder 3)
        - San Francisco Examiner, 20 May (Box 28, Folder 4)
        - Contra Costa Times Editorial Board, 21 May (Box 28, Folder 5)
        - California issues (Box 28, Folder 6)
        - Child care (Box 28, Folder 7)
        - Crime (Box 28, Folder 8)
        - Education K-12 (Box 29, Folder 1)
      - Background papers
        - Budget (Box 29, Folder 2-3)
        - California (Box 29, Folder 4-6)
        - Checchi, Al, [see also SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS-Political activities-Miscellaneous] (Box 30, Folder 1)
        - Crime (Box 30, Folder 2)
        - Davis, Gray (Box 30, Folder 3)
        - Education (Box 30, Folder 4-7)
        - Environment and water policy (Box 30, Folder 8)
        - Propositions and initiatives (Box 31, Folder 1)
        - Transportation (Box 31, Folder 2)
        - Welfare reform (Box 31, Folder 3)
      - Speeches (Box 31, Folder 4-5)
      - Working files
        - 1998 California election calendar (Box 31, Folder 6)
        - California governor's race (Box 31)
          - Part 1 (Box 31, Folder 7-8)
          - Part 2 (Box 32, Folder 1-2)
        - Communication Workers of America (CWA) (Box 32, Folder 3)
        - Early childhood (Box 32, Folder 4)
        - Endorsements (Box 32, Folder 5-9)
        - Fair Housing Act (Box 33, Folder 1)
        - Issues (Box 33, Folder 2)
        - Opposition research - Checchi (Box 33, Folder 3)
        - Position papers (Box 33, Folder 4)
        - Primary returns (Box 33, Folder 5)
        - Service Employees International Union (SEIU) (Box 33, Folder 6)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 33, Folder 7)
      - Media activities
        - Clippings: general, profiles, Q & A's, convention (Box 33, Folder 8-11)